[Music]
so welcome everybody to invoices with
her baby I'm very pleased to be having a
virtual meeting where I'm started called
virtual campfire with Thomas Bjorkman
Thomas reached out to me a while back he
was watching her waiting the meeting
process and he he felt that I think he
turned out to be very accurate there was
a tremendous amount of confidence
between his work and my work Thomas has
written two books there I'm aware of
maybe he's written more but these are
the two that's I've been reading this is
excellent and I'm hoping that and then
more recently this this book and these
books I think are really important in
thinking about some added dimensions
to what I've been calling the meeting
crisis and also some added dimensions of
how we can away from it and respond to
it so I'm very excited to have Thomas
here so Thomas welcome and thank you so
much for joining us thank you Jonah
thank you for for having me on your
podcast thank you very much obviously
you know I've had a wonderful voices
with Ricky with Lehman past geography he
said very really insightful things I
want maybe we can start with what's your
take on that and modernism what does
that mean to you and why it's important
to you personally and why is it
important or you know in general given
our current situation yeah
Thank You Jonathan thank you for for
speaking kind a of my my two latest book
here the Nordic secret I should mention
that I written that one together with my
friend and colleague Lynn Anderson
Danish philosopher Anna and otter
and then I should also mention that
actually the first book I wrote which I
think is becoming more and more relevant
actually was coming out of the
banking world I've been an investment
for for for many years and before that I
was in mathematics and physics and using
then my mathematical and the skills are
modeling in Investment Banking
so when I left Investment Banking a bit
more than ten years ago and set up my
own foundation in Stockholm B Oak Island
Foundation a credit the first book I
wrote is called the market myth and it's
really my experience from the inside in
the market as an investment banker for
more than twenty years thinking about
the strengths the strength of the market
yes because of course the market is a
incredibly strength strength strong
human invention but we should remember
that it is a human invention it's not a
natural phenomena but also we have I
think that I argue in that book put a
little bit too much faith in the market
and the market has sort of become a
guiding star for all human activities in
in a way that the market is not just
suitable to accomplish so as good at
market is in many ways the market is
cannot help us with a number of things
and I think that is at least here in
Scandinavia becoming very evident now in
their kovat crisis where we in
Scandinavia has sort of privatized the
most aspects of health care and medicine
and all of that and it comes a little
bit as a surprise now to the society
that the market has not really been able
to provide those buffers and been able
to be long-term enough to help us in
this crisis so that was the first book I
wrote and then you mentioned the market
myth
which sorry you mentioned the Nordic
secret which is about yeah which is a
which is about the fact that we in the
Nordic countries actually had very
visionary politicians and intellectuals
a hundred to 150 years ago who really
saw the connection between personal
inner development and our ability to
make meaning I would say and societal
change and how this insight really
helped to lift all the Nordic countries
from being the the poorest non
democratic agrarian countries 150 years
ago to become just a few generations
later they're happiest richest most
stable democracies in in the world and
that was really this focus on on in the
development so making a long story short
there what we did back then was that we
started actually a huge number of what I
sometimes jokingly called retreat
centers all over Scandinavia and we
later on made it possible for young
adults in their twenties to spend six
months at one of these centers with the
expressed aim of developing your inner
capacities to be able to act as what we
today might call conscious co-creators
in the creation of of modernity and a
democracy so that's that's quite quite
quite an amazing story and and and not
that well-known and then in the world
that we created you sort of went through
also this historical analysis sort of a
sequence of normativity x' you know
there was the norma to be alone religion
and god and then there was a normativity
coming out of order natee around you
know science and then you say that has
fallen under critique with
post-modernism
and this dovetailed with your firstborn
that has left the market as sort of the
fact of default normativity governing
everybody but as for recent you have
already articulated well it does a lot
of things it can't do everything and we
shouldn't we shouldn't be a lie it we
shouldn't let it be that kind of mob
salute normativity for us so this takes
me back to so what what do you see or
trying to get beyond the postmodern
critique and we're trying to get to a
place where we realize sources of
normativity other than the market one of
the things you point out in the nordic
secret was exactly that network right
that you know there was was a cultural
project that network of retreat centers
almost like secular monasteries where
people were going in order to you know
was individually and collectively
engaged and kind of you know profound
transformation and cultivate what I
would call wisdom you know ability to
get a reflective awareness of their own
self-deception and inculcate rationality
enhance the capacity for meaning making
so what I'm what I'm trying to now us to
put it sort of it bring it to a point
thomas is how does all of this excellent
work that you've done and you I would
you know I got the term from you nor the
meta-crisis we know people are now using
about coated which I think use a little
bit more credit for the idea of the
meta-crisis about systemic interweaving
of crises and like one of the think of
it is doing is disclosing that's this
systemic meta-crisis so what does all of
this now what's the connection between
all of this beautiful analysis and well
I'll use your term you know the matter
crisis how do we how do we take what
you've given us and how do we apply it
to the meta crisis is that a question
yeah absolutely and I mean that that's
really how my thinking and writing has
been
has been going it has really been a
starting point of from analyzing the
market and looking at the market as as a
phenomenon as a human-made phenomenon
that has almost been deified at least we
had we have deferred a lot of normative
power to the market that the market does
not have at all really so that brought
me into thinking it about how we
socially construct this world and the
starting point of it the world we create
is really as you say it's a historical
description of how we as humans
developed this unique capacity for
humans to construct a symbolic universe
yes through our through our language we
cannot some animals can can use what you
could call an index language which means
that they could have one sound for one
type of enemy approaching and another
sound indicating another natural
phenomena but what is unique with the
human symbolic language is that we can
abstract from that concrete level and
and have concepts that has really no
correspondence to the physical reality
so for example a stone or a tree of
course has correspondence in the
physical reality but there is no
correspondence for justice beauty
democracy money money corporations
nation-states or all of these things are
in fact a result from our human ability
to construct a symbolic language and
with the help of this symbolic language
we can start creating a symbolic
universe or a what some sociologist
would call a social imaginary or even
better a collective imaginary yeah
something that comes from our
imagination but
Ritt collectively and this is a unique
human ability and it's easier to see
this collective imaginary if we look at
other societies than ourselves if we
look at a pre-modern society or even an
indigenous society then we could see
this collective imaginary how you can be
start believing in concepts like spirits
and totem and deities and and we can a
bit a bit look down on that and think
that that is naive and so on but my
point is really that this collective
imaginary is something that is evolving
throughout human history and very often
it's evolving more or less linearly but
at some points in human history we
outgrow our collective imaginary and
then we have a huge transformation of
our whole social world and I think and
that's why I think that them the meta
crisis is is a useful concept because
now we realize that all these different
crises is that we see today that the
environment a crisis political crisis or
or psychological crisis that they cannot
be addressed individually because the
crisis is on such a fundamental level
that it is really in our collective
imaginary and that the collective
imaginary that we are living under today
which we got essentially from from the
Enlightenment transition when we went
from a dogmatic religious way of looking
at the world to a rationalistic
scientific way of looking at the world
and and this worldview this collective
imaginary has of course been extremely
powerful and useful for humanity because
it has given us modern medicine and
human rights and democracy and all of
that that we would never want to be
without but then at the
time I believe that we have now used
them the capacity they are mean we reach
the end of the capacity of this both
worldview and collective imaginary and
that we are at this transition point in
our social global system and from
physics I I have got this model of
self-organizing complex systems and
thinking in systems theory and thinking
in self-organizing systems I think that
is so useful to do that and that that is
something that is applicable of course
not just a natural science phenomena but
also to your field of cognition yes to
see the mind not as some sort of the in
machine made out of neurons but much
more like a self-organizing dynamic
system that has the potential for
evolution and evolving throughout our
lives and if you look at culture in the
same way you look at culture as a
self-organizing complex system then you
realize that this can evolve but then
also that you come to one of these
eventually come to one of these
transition points phase shifts points or
bifurcation points where system needs a
radical transformation that usually
entails either a breakdown in complexity
or a break through to a more complex
more elegant way of of organizing and I
think that's that's where we are right
now humanity we are at one of these
bifurcation points and now it's either
breakthrough or break down cultural
culture as a dynamical system and I was
thinking about you know one of the
phenomena studies you
site and you know you've been framing
things in a particular way and your
frame tells you what's salient
irrelevant and then you get to a point
where that framing is actually
supporting you yeah or dies in
criticality doesn't become pretty funny
you know critical it brings down entropy
increases for a while you get you get
that phase of criticality and as you say
criticality criticality can either mean
that the system collapses as you said
ghosts or low estate or what happens in
insight is right the criticality breaks
the structure up enough so that a new
structure becomes possible because you
get a high experience and of course if
you do this on a real large scale with
your mind that that's when you have this
sort of inner transformation or you have
a method and metanoia yes and as and as
with all self-organizing complex system
in in these transitions you have the
possibility of emergence yes yes
something come something completely new
emerges back yes there should not really
predict nor explain in the previous
state of on the complex system and and
that really for me as a physicist that
really made me understand that personal
in the transformation a metanoia is
actually possible
I mean before before that I thought that
this was some sort of religious answer
you know a New Age spirituality but now
I can see how this is actually the
probably the the the most
straightforward way for nature to
organize consciousness it is it is to
provide a general function that would
then take in and process information and
energy and then use that to
self-organize and then to transform that
that would be the natural way for nature
to
very efficient way she achieved
consciousness and that's what I was
exactly trying to propose with the
insight because what happens in insight
is you get a new function that's what
the higher you get the emergence new
understanding emergence of new options
and so the idea that the culture might
be at that point and also you you put
your finger I'm working on a book called
the cognitive continuum
you know from insight all the way up to
you know enlightenment how the state
machine or you can see the same
machinery at different scales of
analysis and complexity when we look at
cognition so there's a there's the same
issue that's happening in the HAR moment
as you said it's systemic and more
comprehensive but that's what's
ultimately happening with people are
going through Maranoa the deeply
transformative experiences so yes
absolutely
and now if we then talk about society
and our collective imaginary I think
that we now are at the point again of
criticality where we need to have such a
transformation such a collective
Metanoia yeah yeah and we should
remember and I spend the first part of
my book the world we create in in
showing that humanity has or different
cultures has gone through the sorts of
processes many many times when we sort
of went from going back to your original
question when we went from sort of an
indigenous tribal society a
hunter-gatherer society into a
pre-modern civilization and then from
the pre-modern civilization into
modernity and now we are through post
modernity transitioning into something
beyond the post modernity that we might
call meta modernity or whatever we would
like to to call that and and then of
course it becomes important to ask
ourselves this question what what is it
then the system that is about to
transform
what is this collective imaginary and
how does the transformation of this
collective imaginary relate to our
individual transformations and
consciousness and and ability to hold
and replicate this collective imaginary
and the first thing of course that that
is makes this so very difficult is that
we do not really today outside academic
circles of of anthropologists and
sociologists we don't have a everyday
language for this collective imaginary I
mean for for for for all of us this
collective imaginary is like the water
for the fish yes it's something we swim
in and we take it for granted but we
don't really think about it right but of
course what's different from from the
fish in the water is that for the fish
the water is a natural phenomenon that
it's not aware of whereas for us this
collective imaginary is not a natural
phenomenon it is a human-made phenomenon
but mostly made out of our unconscious
reproduction and slow evolution of what
we inherit from previous generations
exactly I mean culture is part of this
collective a imaginary so is our
worldview everything at the market is a
very important part of our collective
imaginary previous collective
imaginaries then of course God and
religion took up a large part of that
collective imaginary and and what is
interesting with these collective
imaginaries is that we as humans have
got this tremendous collective freedom
to come up with almost any collective
imaginary we could think of and if going
back in history of course I mean going
back just
thousand years going going back a couple
of thousand years there were literally
sounds or tens of thousands independent
cultures that we're living in that
completely own collective imaginary and
and then through a bit of Darwinistic
competition between various collective
imaginary some proved stronger and
survived like for example Judaism has
been able to survive as a collective
imaginary for for for such a long time
whereas other competing collective
imaginaries from 3,000 years ago has has
gone extinct so so that is amazing that
we have this freedom to create all of
this but that also creates a problem
because we need for a society to
function we need to live in the same
roughly the same collective imaginary
for us even to be able to coordinate
communicate and direct the actions of
the collective so how do we sort of it
fix this collective imaginary and then
sociologists have come up and this is
one of the important postmodern insight
is both the existence and the importance
of these socially constructed realities
and narratives involved and the
meta-narratives involved in these
structures to realize that these are
really human constructions but at the
same time that we construct these
realities these imaginaries we also have
to fix them somewhere and that is what
the sociologist sometimes calls the
ultimate authority yes in that
collective imaginary and of course in
the pre-modern world that ultimate
authority was you usually God so it's
not just having a random world
have you had the ultimate explanation
why is the world in this way it is
because God has created it in this way
why should we believe in these Ten
Commandments it's not just that Moses
and he thought they were good no they
need to be absolutely if we should fix
the collective imaginary so we need to
say they are given by God and then when
we stop believing in God as an ultimate
authority during the Enlightenment and
we got this this rationalistic scientist
scientific worldview then science took a
bit the role in our society as this
ultimate authority we were looking for
the scientific explanation and the
scientific answer but then of course
with post modernity we start to realize
that even science is in some important
ways the social construct and that
science do not have every answer so what
happens then and then of course
interestingly enough post modernity does
not come up with its own ultimate
authority and then as you pointed out
earlier I argue in my book that the fact
that in the postmodern worldview where
we realize thee that all these
collective imaginaries and narratives
are human constructs then our social
imaginary becomes completely not
anchored any longer and we need to
following yeah we need to find some sort
of anchor point and that's where the
market comes in and of course the
postmodern philosophers are very
critical to towards the market but
somehow the market sleeps in the the
back door as a default because there is
no other ultimate authority so then
today it's natural when we ask why is
the world the way it is why is it that
an investment banker earns five or ten
times the salary of a university
professor well it's the market market
has the answer
so yeah what should we produce well the
market world will tell you that and then
we started to put a lot of authority
into the market and again a little bit
too much and we are now starting to
realize
so so then of course the question
becomes done so if we had this
pre-modern world with its collective
imaginary and with God as the ultimate
authority then we had the modern world
with science as the ultimate authority
now a postmodern transition where the
market has taken up too much power and
are we starting to realize that what
will be the next step what will come out
of this what sort of worldview what sort
of social imaginary and and what sort of
ultimate authority will will emerge here
and I wish I could have had an answer on
that I wish I could have an answer on
that but but you can only speculate but
but just realizing that we are on this
evolutionary path and that we are at
this very very critical point in history
because the previous times where we have
had civilizations collapsing and
collective imaginaries collapsing there
has always been other competing
contenders that have been sort of then
given the space to rise up and take the
power of our civilization but now we are
really interconnected in one global
civilization and that again from the
virus right now that becomes evident to
everyone that we we only have one world
and we more or less only have one
collective imaginary as well now and if
that one is falling apart I would argue
that then we cannot just trust natural
selection and random walk we actually
need to to make a conscious step into
something new and that will be a
collective leap a little bit of a
collective leap of faith into something
that we do not know what it is but we
need to dare to let go
and and collectively take a leap that
was a fantastic synoptic integration of
your argument thank you for that will
you lay that out a couple things came to
mind you know as within a collective
imaginary and how deeply interwoven with
you know you know interpersonal and
intrapersonal transformation and and so
I'll use a term that I'm happy with but
we don't have an alternate one right now
there seems to be an important spiritual
dimension to everything and we have that
even things that seem so bottom line
like the market have a lot of almost
numinous like deity aspect when people
serve the market and the might have yes
the bars the way the world is and so it
seems to me that part of what we are
talking about then is well at least all
they can point it out but that arguing
for it is that and I know you're not
claiming this you're not claiming we can
unlearn everything that these previous
revolutions have given us we can sort of
go back like to an indigenous world we
can't go back to an axial world right so
similarly we can't unlearn science so it
sounds like part of the project has to
be to overcome some of the divides that
were so fundamental to the grammar of
the collective imaginary that we're
falling down that's falling down like
the divides between science and
spirituality the device reminded body
the divides between you know you know
subjectivity and objectivity the divides
between you know my own personal space
and and my own personal cognition and a
distributed cognition and what I see is
one of the differences eyes these
post-modernism called those questions
called those divides into question but
what I see a lot of people doing your
work my work that people are talking
with
with is we're trying to go from oh yes
yes those divisions don't work but
simply criticizing them is insufficient
what we have to do is actually what does
it look like to go beyond those device
which back science spirituality try to
stitch back you know that you know the
mind of the body and the person in the
world and so although I don't I think
that there is a that there's a both/and
situation yes yeah here again we need we
need to go beyond the divides but then
also the divides can some sometimes be
be be helpful and what we definitely
need to do is that that in the
postmodern insights that that all of
these things are just human construct
we tend on tend to mix everything and
put everything on the same footing and
your sailor things like every
perspective is equally valid in every
situation and things like that and and
and that is of course not the case so
for example if we look at our world
today so today for me as an individual I
am equally dependent on air to breathe
on oxygen and on money to survive in
today's society I need to have oxygen
and I need to have money but we also
need to understand that they are
fundamentally two different kinds of
things they are ontologically different
even if I as an individual me as an
individual I am totally dependent on
oxygen and on money we as a collective
even if every person on earth came
together and we decided that we do not
want as humans to be dependent on oxygen
we we can't do it we can't do it but if
we came together everyone
on the earth or even just everyone in a
nation-state and said we don't want to
be depending on money any long we want
to invent some new mechanism to allocate
the goods in society money would be gone
tomorrow so it's a fundamental
difference between between a natural
phenomenon like oxygen and the socially
constructed thing as money but what is
sad yes and is that in many cases we mix
this up so we tend to believe that that
the planetary boundaries is something
that is up for negotiation whereas the
market forces
we just need to obey well of course it's
completely different I mean the
planetary boundaries will always be
there whereas the market forces is
actually under our collective agency we
can change them but we need to do that
on a on a collective level so so yes in
one way the distinctions are important
but then on another way of course every
distinction is Justin and some sort of
arbitrary perspective of the world
because at the end of the day as you
point out there is only one
interconnected system it's just one
system but it's very very difficult to
comprehend and take decisions if you
need to keep the whole of the universe
from Big Bang until the end of the
universe in mind so then of course it's
a very it's a strong tool we have in for
example science and physics to
understand that if we are looking at a
stone falling to the ground
we don't think actually to understand
that particular aspect needs to take
everything in the universe into account
there are no gods interfering in that
the stone does not have a
it's a very simple equation and of
course that is strong so sometimes it's
very it's it's very powerful and very
strong to have these analytical ability
to divide this complex world into small
small pieces but then in other cases
it's devastating and we need and we need
to see it all as a as a one system
interacting and that is that system also
includes the for example the of
subjective experiences of our
consciousness
so in this totality of the world there
is there are those natural object
objects there is our subjective
experiences that has got real impact on
our action and therefore impact on the
world but then also the compass the
collective subjectivity that we have put
into the collective imaginary and we
reified into some sort of social reality
that meets us as individuals as almost
as objective reality as as the stone or
the water introduced I agree with you
that simply letting the complexity fall
away is not what we want the criticality
to give us so what what what I hear you
saying is you know there's there's these
there's a you know there's a scientific
aspect there's a like I said this
broadly spiritual part of what I'm
understanding what I'm proposing to you
is what are the meta modern
understanding of spirituality is a
recognition and reappropriation of our
agency within the collective imaginary
and turning back towards the project of
the skating with this and this and this
and then and but then what you're now
saying it
addition to that is we have to you have
to take great ontological care in how
we're trying to do the the both end
we're trying to get beyond we don't want
to simply remove the distinction that
are actually necessary for for you know
appropriately engaging in the
reappropriation we don't work inflate
yes I think yes I think that in in in in
post modernity we have this sort of
relativistic perspective title that
every perspective is equally valid I
think the next step is some sort of
integrated perspectivism saying that for
any problem the more angles the more
perspectives you can view this this
situation from the more information you
will get out but it's very important to
discern the how important the different
angles are in on analyzing a certain a
certain phenomena so it's not that then
yeah you need as many perspectives as
possible but then it's a little bit more
complicated and just float throwing them
all in in in in a bucket and picking one
randomly no you need to understand what
sort of a information each perspective
is best at best at providing different
perspectives given to you by the
different disciplines the entities they
look at the language they use the type
of methods they use and you're not
trying to reduce them all to one
modernist thing you're not trying to
reduce all the data for science or like
but what you're trying to do is afford
you know a conceptual a conceptual
vocabulary Rio Grande
so that instead of them right right I'm
not trying to reduce them all in one
perspective and I'm not just saying
although they have nothing to do with
each other I'm trying to afford a
synoptic integration for that they can
talk to each other mutually inform and
mutually transform each other
so I think you get the date day right
that's how at least I'm trying to
understand how we can steer between you
know trying to get a mono perspective or
just saying well all the perspectives
they they're only commensal they don't
have anything to do with each other
they're all equally good it's
fundamental presupposition behind
they're actually atomically isolated
from each other I know I think the mono
perspective and the atomic we isolated
idea I think those are both false yes
for reasons and so trying to get finding
as you say you know you know when you
try to do something you're trying to
remember the differences because they're
important because you know neuroscience
can do things that psychology just can't
do and vice versa
but they also need to talk to each other
they need to be able to transform and
inform each other and so that's the
model I'm trying to get you know what
how do you try to go forward we try to
take that that skillset of bridging so
we can get you know this dynamic
convergence between perspectives and see
we can scale that up to the more
comprehensive perspectives that are in
our culture right now that's nice that's
all I'm trying to a word of way of
responding for people yeah absolutely
and and as as as many writers have
pointed out so far in in history when we
have gone from one collective imaginary
or one paradigm of of worldview to the
next one but we have usually completely
disregarded the the previous worldview
and we have even developed allergy
against it it's a bit like it's a bit
like also when we as humans grow I mean
the teenager does not at all what to
recognize the child he or she was three
years ago
but as a really mature person you should
be able to integrate yes your experience
is to live without these reactions so so
when we went from and from a tribal
society into a pre-modern monotheistic
religious society everything tribal was
by Barry and and was sort of pushed away
and when we went during the
Enlightenment into the rational
scientific worldview everything from
religion and spirituality through now
and again with the postmodern way of
thinking then we are throwing out
science and and and everything so what
we need to do now there's a starting
point at least of course as many have
pointed out is that we need to try to
integrate the insights the very strong
insights of all these different ways or
modalities or perspectives of viewing
the human life and society and situation
without bringing in the limitations and
try to get some sort of integral and
that's of course very integral comes
from an integral perspective on on the
world but I don't think it's just that
then we also have that then we also have
this emergent phenomena that we don't
really know where what what it is so it
will just it may not just be an
integration of this as some there will
be something more elegant emerging after
this as well they simultaneously
integrate and differentiate complexify
that's when you get emergent functions
and Gabi I think trying to afford
complexification within the synoptic
integration is a way of trying to not
cause but trying to afford that
emergence make a space and that there is
where I think that the connection
between our personal inner growth and
development the complexification
our cognitive system or our total sort
of inner system the complication of our
total inner system plays an important
role in facilitating the transition the
break through to a new more complex and
perhaps also more elegant way of
organizing our society a more complex
and elegant way because in in any any of
these different states of the evolution
of human human society there needs to be
a possibility for enough many people in
the population to actively engage with
the culture and with a collective
imaginary otherwise it would just be a
dead dead book or something you need to
have so you need to have some and I
don't know where where this you need to
have five or ten percent at least in the
population that are really on a
cognitive and emotional level of
complexity to really understand and
engage and actively not not just
passively reproduce but actively be able
to reproduce and develop this so I think
that the most important thing that we
could actually do to help this emergence
of a new more complex civilization is to
again just like we did in Scandinavia
and the Nordic secret then the Nordic
secret is to help a critical number of
people to mature enough to be able to
participate in actively participate as
co-creators as enlightened as conscious
co-creators of this new society this
Newark
collective imaginary and again just like
with a with the Nordic society this the
the amount of people necessary I think
is dependent on their distribution in
society and the beauty with the Nordic
secret was that these 10% of each
generation that were able to participate
in these personal development activities
retreats they were actually from all
sorts of social backgrounds so they were
middle class but also a lot of
working-class and from the farming part
of population so you ended up with 10%
fairly evenly distributed in society and
I think that that has much much larger
possibility to succeed and even having
20% in some sort of isolated elite of
society so that's where we are again
helping enough many people to develop
the inner capacities to become conscious
co-creators of the next level Honor
Society yeah I usually say that I don't
I don't see the the Nordic secret the
Nordic experience as a blueprint for
what we should do today we could
certainly do this in other ways we might
not have to create these reach small
retreat sensors out in nature even if I
believe strong in that concept and that
is what we are doing at the Oak Island
foundation but weak it could be done in
different in different ways today and
and I'm for example involved in a
digital platform you have to facilitate
personal development called 29k dot-org
so I think that we might be able to do
to use digital tools to help facilitate
this so it's not a
blueprint but it is certainly a case
study yes showing that this is not a
fantasy this has actually worked and it
and it worked differently but he worked
well in both Denmark and Norway and
Sweden and that was three different
implementations and fairly independent
implementation but about the same time
and it worked beautifully in all three
and we and we still see even though
we've forgotten about this and they even
if we are starting to lose it I'm the
first one to say that is well that we
are starting to do sit-in in the
Scandinavian countries we still see the
effect this the effort was it was not
just one culture but three different
countries is almost like a scientific
study on a full-scale sighting in three
different societies a bit different
implementation and then measure this
over fifty hundred years and see what
happens and you can see that it worked
of course now of course now this was
going from a pre-modern society into a
modern society now we're going from a
modern or postmodern society into some
something new so then this becomes even
more important but perhaps also more
challenging for us as individuals
because this becomes more and more
complex and you need to be able to hold
more and more perspectives and the
emotions and we are going from a
monocultural society into a
multicultural society and that
complexified things a lot so this
becomes even more important down yeah
you're not proposing this as some rigid
template that we just transposed from
the past and now you're taking it as
right as really as you said you know
the powerfully comprehensive historical
case study that tells us that something
like this is possible and that's an
alternative to the kind of utopianism
you're not oh here's my vision of the
future
and I can guarantee that if you just do
X Y and Zed but if we just do this right
that's a toilet area look you're not
doing that at all you're saying no no
I'm saying we're going through a change
there's something deeply analogous let's
try and make the analogy as best we can
to where we are right now I think that's
a very important or idiom to both a
nostalgia it says no let's go back
somehow let's get back to the develop
this world right or no no utopianism it
said I know for sure what the future
looks like it denies the importance of
your job and that and that is also of
course on why this transition is is in
many ways more more difficult than the
previous one from pre modernity into
modernity and it's not just that we have
these sort of emergence the emergent
phenomena that we need to leave leave
space for it's not just that we have the
technological rapid rapid evolution that
we do not really know what society what
the technological possibilities will be
in just 10 years and I think that the
future arrangement of society and
especially the next implementation of
the market and of democracy I think that
that will be very much dependent on
development in for example blockchain
technology and another thing so exactly
what this will be we will truly be an
emergent but there's one more thing that
complicates things and and that is that
a hundred years ago it was actually
possible at least plausible to argue for
a utopia saying that that this is where
we want to be in 20 years so in 50 50
years let's go there and it's it's
easier
to bring up support for an idea when you
can clearly articulate an end state and
of course we can't do that because of
the rapid technological development
because of the emergent properties of of
the future but also because I believe
that the future will be that rapidly
constantly evolving that instead of the
future being a state I think we have to
realize that the future will be a
process ok so our idea about the future
is not about a future state it is it's
not about supporting the emergence of a
future state it's it's supporting the
emergence of a good future evolutionary
process where we become self conscious
about the importance of integrating the
inner personal development and actively
integrating the co-creation the emergent
co-creation of our collective imaginary
as well which we're trying to get to the
state the completion the production
though those ways of understanding how
we're going to move into the future but
it's difficult because again as you
mentioned many times in your theories
our human mind is not made for for these
things I mean we want to see the simple
solution we want to see a picture of
where we are going we want to know what
is right and what is wrong
so it puts a huge demand on not not only
the thought leaders of societies and the
philosophers but also really on every
person in society that that should be
part of the democratic process
of society about so education and our
support this society supports for for
everyone to be able to develop the inner
capacities to be part of this I think
that is super important if we are not
going to end up with a two-tier society
or something like that well you know
just talking everybody should know this
no Thomas is out there trying to
actually you know put it into into
existence all these things that he's
talking about you should know that time
you know in a sense you're running a lot
of the case studies that need to be run
yeah I think that's what we need to do
now we need to prototype yeah we need to
experiment that we need to prototype I
mean what is it like to be creating a
collating space for example where where
you try to create a culture that is a
deliberative developmental culture a
culture that is actually holding
everyone's development and trying to
bring out the best in every first how do
you create such a culture on the small
scale how do you experiment with these
things so that's it's funny it's funny
it they're there to work with these
things this has been really really great
you know you were able to well I'm
grateful that you were here and you do
so you articulate your vision so much
because I want more people to be aware
of your work and what you're thinking
and and also as I just mentioned what
you're doing and what's happening so I
wanted to ask you there's any sort of
final summative not to bring things to
completion any final summit you want to
say no I I think it's
that we we try to stay open in in rapid
change and when we have virus or war
it's very easy to to want to shut down
to go back yes yes shut down go back
okay but we know that there is no no
going back there is a lot to learn from
history there is a continuing continued
continuity there is a continuum that we
shouldn't we should realize the
important of our roots and the more well
we know our roots the more rooted we are
the more free we are to explore and
experiment and and to dare those leaps
of faith
mostly individually so faith but also
the collective ones that we are now
facing the market myth yep it also
Thomas has some YouTube videos that are
out there that maybe Thomas you can send
me some links for things I can put on
each of the notes for this video so
people can get more in contact with with
your work so I will do that John so
thank you for a very nice conversation
Oh